第15集
通信技术试验卫星三号
在轨活动
Welcome to Spacecast.
欢迎来到Spacecast节目
原视频名：TJS 3 Space Activities - Spacecast 15
原作者名：AGI, An Ansys Company
视频来源：youtu.be/xx5zevd6AdU
原视频发布日期：20190701
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
I'm Josh and I'm back with my friend Bob Hall
我是Josh 我和我的朋友Bob Hall一起回来了
who is the director of operations for the ComSpOC, the commercial space operations center.
他是ComSpOC(商业航天任务中心)的运营主管
In the ComSpOC has global network of sensors
ComSpOC有着全球的传感器网络
that they take that data and they process it.
可以利用这些数据进行处理
and they come up with a catalogue of all the things in space.
然后得到包含所有空间物体的目录
And so Bob spends a lot of time watching what's going on
那么Bob花了很多时间来观察太空里发生的事件
particularly in GEO
特别是地球同步轨道(GEO)轨道上的
and seeing what satellites are doing and their maneuvers and where they're going
看看卫星每天都在做什么 还有它们的机动和要去的地方
and what they're doing to change their orbits on a daily basis
以及它们的轨道是如何改变的
and who they're coming close to.
还有它们正在接近的物体
So Bob is here to talk to us again about something interesting that he's been keeping an eye on.
那么Bob在这里再次和我们谈谈 他一直在关注的一些有趣的事情
Bob welcome.
欢迎Bob
Thanks Josh.
谢谢你 Josh
And today you're gonna be talking about one that I don't know much about.
今天你要讲的是一个我不太了解的卫星
The TJS-3 satellite you want to give a little background on what that guy is?
是通信技术试验卫星三号(TJS-3)卫星 你能不能介绍一下这颗卫星的背景
So yeah TJS-3 is a Chinese satellite
那么好吧 TJS-3是Chinese satellite
as a Chinese by all reports a Chinese military mission
根据所有的报告显示 这是一个Chinese military mission
and by all reports mean open source.
而这里 根据所有的报告是指公开的消息
Yeah I think it's a Chinese secret mission
是的 我认为这是一个Chinese secret mission
meaning they're not gonna tell the world where it is.
这是指他们不会告诉世界这颗卫星在哪儿
I mean that's not unusual.
我是指 这很常见
Lots of countries have secret satellites that they don't want to tell people where it is.
很多国家都有保密卫星 他们不想告诉人们它在哪里
And this was launched late in December.
这颗卫星是在12月下旬(20181225)发射的
and got up to GEO right around January firstish or so.
并在1月1日左右到达GEO
The interesting thing is it showed up in GEO
有趣的是 它(直接)出现在GEO上
earth-centered, earth-fixed(ECEF) = 地心地固坐标系 / 非惯性地球静止参考系(av543824424 03:21)
地球地下的运动 = 指排除地质运动的地球自转的运动
and I'm showing the the orbit here in a earth fixed frame
那么我在这里的轨道显示在相对地球静止的画面中
so that with respect to the subsurface of the earth how the satellites moving.
也就是卫星相对地球地下的运动
That's one Rev there one day.
(对于GEO) 就是一天一周期
The interesting thing is that there was this other object that showed up with it from the launch.
有趣的是 还有另一个物体 从发射的时候就和它一起出现了
Now China to the best of my knowledge still has not announced a second payload.
那么据我所知 目前为止China仍然没有宣布第二个有效载荷
In other words that they never said that there was another satellite being launched.
换句话说 他们从未说过另一颗卫星被一起发射
And so by default the way it went into the public catalog, the US public catalog.
那么在默认情况下 它进入了US空间物体公共目录
It was given the name of a TJS-3 AKM.
它被赋予了一个叫TJS-3 AKM的名字
AKM stems for Apogee Kick Motor which is an upper stage.
AKM意为远地点点火发动机 也就是一种上面级
It's one type of upper stage
它是一种上面级
that could be used to deliver satellite to let's say GEO.
可用于把卫星送到 比如说GEO
And then once it's done, it is usually disposed of.
然后一旦任务完成 它通常会被丢弃
So it's often times what you will do is you will,
那么很多时候 你会这样做
let's say, you use the AKM to get close to GEO.
假设 你用AKM接近GEO
You get off the AKM and the AKM does a final maneuver and is dead.
你从AKM上下来 AKM完成了最后的机动 然后就死了
And then the satellite uses its own thrusters to move a little bit into GEO.
接着卫星用它自己的推进器 只花一点点功夫来进入GEO
The AKM took you like 99% of the way there or 99 a half
AKM带你走了99%的路 甚至是99.5%的路
and AKM then it's left in a non GEO orbit.
而AKM就会被留在一个非GEO的轨道上
It's not in an orbit that it's no collision risk.
它处在一个没有碰撞风险的轨道上
Right.
没错
For the 500 active GEO's of the world which is kind of pricey real estate.
对于这世界上500颗活跃的GEO卫星来说 轨道资源是一种昂贵的资源
So difference number one is besides the fact it wasn't announced, this thing is perfectly in GEO.
那么第一点不同的是 除了其位置没有被公布 这东西完全处在GEO上
That's the blue guy here.
也就是图里轨迹为蓝色的物体
And in fact it wasn't announced this is a typical that's what you're clear.
而事实上 如你所说 位置没有被公布是完全正常的
If it's just an upper stage that's okay.
如果这只是一个上面级 倒也无妨
People don't necessarily announce upper stages.
人们一般不必公布上面级的位置
So that's why it was named this way.
所以才会这样命名
mm-hmm
恩
But again that the Chinese didn't name it.
但同样地 原发射国并没有对此命名
The catalog comes in the US
而目录是US搞的
and with no claim essentially that it's something else that's what the US named it.
而US在起名字的时候基本上不用将其声称为别的什么东西
Okay fine.
好吧
But again it's perfectly in GEO.
但它又是完全在GEO的
So you see it's going up and down here. Very very small.
那么你看它在这里上上下下 但运动幅度非常非常小
It's really not inclined.
它几乎没有倾角
This north-south motion is small.
这个南北向的运动是较小的
This is a very tiny inclination.
这是一个非常小的倾角
What you would see with an operational satellite.
就像你在运营中的卫星上看到的那样
It's coplanar meaning it's perfectly in sync with TJS-3.
运动轨迹是共面的 意味着它与TJS-3是完全同步的
that also is not necessarily unusual if the two objects came from the same launch.
这也可能是正常的 如果两个物体是被一起发射的话
The fact that they're left at the same inclination.
事实上 它们的倾角是一样的
Okay.
好的
But yet you don't leave a dead upper stage here.
但是留下的上面级并不是死的
On purpose.
而且是有意的
So that was weird.
所以那是挺怪的
Yeah.
是的
Very weird.
非常奇怪
And you see that they are at this instant I paused at 93 kilometers apart from each other.
你看 我暂停下来 在这一瞬间 这俩相距93km
And you'll see that number changes.
而你也会看到这个数字的变化
And so what I'm dragging through January here if you watch the clock in the lower left
那么看下左下角的时钟 我现在把时间拖过1月份
you see what's happening.
你会看到发生了什么
They're drifting drifting.
他们正在漂移
Now by this time.
那么在这个时候
I kind of went right over it.
时间拖得有点过度了
January 4th we saw this AKM thing do a maneuver so that was unusual.
1月4日 我们看到这个AKM做了一个机动 那么这是不寻常的
And then January 10th it did another maneuver.
然后在1月10日 它又做了一次机动
So again if it was an upper stage a spent upper stage from a end of December mission.
那么 如果它是一个在之前12月底任务中失效的上面级
There's no way it's doing maneuvers on January 4th and 10th.
它是不可能在1月4日和10日做机动的
So that also got our attention.
所以这也引起了我们的注意
So now I have a couple things to say this is not an AKM.
那么现在我有几件事要说 此AKM非彼AKM
We also looked at the photometric (heat chart)
我们也看了光度(热图)……
and those maneuvers were not to give it an inclination to get out of the way.
那么这些机动并不是为了让它得到倾角 以离开此地
Right right.
对对对
They were basically station-keeping maneuvers to adjust the the east-west drift.
基本上 它们是在进行保位机动 以抵消东西向的漂移
Notice how these guys are staying kind of in sync.
注意这些家伙是如何保持同步的
I'm going through January here.
我现在正在把时间拖过1月
Now Bob is scrubbing through time if you can see his mouse.
那么Bob在擦动时间条 如果你能看到他的鼠标
My mouse is on bottom so I'm going backwards or forwards.
我的鼠标在画面的底部 那么我在往后或往前走
So now we're around January 19th
那么现在我们到了1月19日左右
and on Saturday the AKM move his wheel.
而在周六 AKM进行了它的机动
It's going somewhere.
它要去某个地方了
And it moved over about a tenth of a degree
它移动了大约0.1度
and two days later on Monday TJS-3 followed.
两天后的周一 TJS-3也跟着来了
So this is but one of many examples where these two guys are operating in concert.
那么这不过是这两个家伙协同行动的众多例子之一
There whatever TJS-3 is which again unannounced whatever.
不管TJS-3是什么 当然 再说一下 TJS-3的任务并没有被公布
This other thing this Mysteries object they're acting in concert.
另一个东西 也就是这个神秘物体 是和TJS-3一起运动的
And so you're going to see they slide to the east a little bit.
所以你会看到它们向东边滑行了一点
And then they both do a station keeping maneuver almost at the same time to go back to the West
然后它们几乎在同一时间做了一个保位的机动 回到了西边
because in this part of the the GEO belt, the forces are such
因为在GEO的这片区域上 存在这样的力
that your satellite will the accelerations to the east.
会使你的卫星向东加速
So you do a maneuver to kick it west and it turns around
那么你做了一个机动动作 把卫星踢到西边 它就转过来了
and you keep doing that over and over again.
而你会这样一直做(来保持位置)
and that's what these guys kept doing.
而这两个家伙也一直在做
So I'm going back and forth and back to establish relationship between these two guys.
那么(在时间的加速下) 这两者一直在这样徘徊 建立了某种联系
Notice the range is generally around 100 km or so.
注意范围一般在100公里左右
So they're not over tight.
所以它们并没有靠得太近
They're not doing a rendezvous and prox ops(proximity operations).
它们没有进行交会以及抵近操作(prox ops)
b23.tv/av543824424，一个绕飞的例子
They're not circling one another.
它们没有互相绕飞
So at this point TJS-3 does its maneuver to kind of half the distance.
那么在此时 TJS-3机动到两者距离的一半
And again look they're operating in perfect concert station-keeping together.
而且同样地 会看到它们在完美地协同行动 一起进行保位
So they've got this established pattern of doing something together.
那么它们建立了这种既定的协同模式
Not sure what it is.
不知道这是在做什么
Not sure whether it sure either one is.
也不知道其中一个物体在做什么
But it's very weird that there was this mystery object.
但非常奇怪的是 这之中存在一个神秘的物体
And it was not a dead object.
而且是活动的
We also looked at the photometry which is the basically the light data.
我们还进行了光度测定 基本上也就是亮度的数据
So we would look at this with telescopes.
那么也就是会用望远镜来看这个东西
Each object has a brightness.
每个物体都有一个亮度
And if you look at the brightness over time
而如果你检查亮度随时间变化的情况
we've got algorithms that will tell us things like the spin period.
我们的算法会告诉我们一些事情 比如物体旋转的周期
Or if it's not spinning.
或者它没在旋转
And we could tell if a thing is if an object is tumbling
同时我们也可以判断一个物体是否在翻转
so when an active GEO has a problem and fails and starts to tumble
所以 当一个活动的GEO卫星出现问题并失效 还开始翻滚的时候
because its attitude is not working, we can see that.
这是因为它的姿态控制系统出现了问题 那么我们就可以发现
We could tell in this case that this thing was not tumbling.
在这种情况下我们可以看出 这个东西不是在翻滚
So again another evidence that it is not a dead thing.
那么这又是一个证据 证明它不是一个死物
Stable attitude.
具有稳定的姿态
So it had this behavior.
那么它有这种行为
A quick question for you Bob.
我想问你一个小问题 Bob
You said that is not rendezvous proximity operations.
你说这不是交会的那种抵近操作
and so it's not close enough to be classified as that
是因为它还不够近 不能被归类为交会
so what would you call it.
所以 你会怎么称呼它
I mean it's kind of rendezvous at a distance.
我是指 它就像是一种远距离交会
Yeah, that's a good question.
是啊 这是一个很好的问题
Um so the reason I'm not calling it rendezvous is they were both dropped off here.
恩 那么我不叫它们交会 是因为它们的距离并没有进一步减少
And they're just acting in a coordinated fashion.
而且他们只是在以一种协调的方式行事
It's not...
这不是...
The destination?
一种目的地？
There were a hundred kilometers apart now.
现在已经相距一百公里了
They're in where I have the screen frozen they're 50 kilometers apart.
它们在我的屏幕暂停的地方 是相距50公里的
If you came from halfway around the world in a park next to a guy at 50,
如果你从世界的另一端来到一个公园里 和另一个人相距50m
you might call that a rendezvous okay.
你可以把这个过程叫做交会对吧
The mission doesn't appear like a prox ops mission.
但这个任务并不像一个抵近操作的任务
It's kind of I guess a subjective use.
这是一种我猜测的可能用途
So now I want to switch to.
那么 现在我想切换到
Now we are in mid-may and they're still doing their thing.
现在我们已经到了5月中旬 它们还在做它们的事情
There's still 50 kilometers apart.
仍然相距50公里
What's the date?
那么具体日期呢？
May 12th or something.
差不多5月12日
Yeah you can see.
是的 你可以看到
So here they are.
那么它们在这里
And they're still doing their thing.
而它们还在做它们的事情
By the way those boxes are just the boxes we assign them based on watching their behavior
顺便说一下 这些方格只是我们根据观察到的它们的行为给它们分配的
where they spent a lot of their time.
它们主要在这些格子里活动
It's just something we put together for ourselves.
这只是方便我们观察设置的
We do that for all GEOs.
我们给所有的GEO卫星都做了这样的事情
And what happened was again on. This is like a Friday.
而接下来发生的事情比较类似 这差不多是在周五
Their inclination wasn't big.
它们的倾角不是很大
I mean I've zoomed way in.
我是指 (这个画面里的轨迹)我是已经放大过了
This little up and down motion wasn't a lot.
实际上这里的上下运动幅度不大
But they did a maneuver.
但是它们做了一个机动
How much is not a lot.
多大的幅度算不大
Tenth of the degree or less.
0.1的度数或者更少
Okay, so 73 km.
好 那么73公里
I'd have to look at what it was.
我得看看是什么
Oh yeah.
哦 对了
No 1/10 of a degree of plane.
这是指0.1度的轨道面改变
Oh okay.
哦 好吧
So they did a manoeuvre literally to the same minute.
那么 它们真的是一分钟内做了同一个机动
So it's like synchronized swimming in space.
那么 这就像是在太空中同步游泳
And you're you're detecting those maneuvers and processing through them when you're watching this.
而你在看这些事件发生的时候 也在检测这些机动 并且处理这些数据
Yes and so.
是的 所以
Do you have a pretty good idea of when this happens as it happens.
你是否能很清楚地预测什么时候会发生这种事？
Yeah absolutely. The software we use to detect maneuvers is
是的 当然 我们用来检测机动的软件是
is really one of the linchpins of our highly accurate catalog.
是我们(制作)高精度目录的关键之一
The ability to with our filter based technology solve for the maneuver
能够用我们基于过滤器的技术来解决机动的问题
and fly through the maneuver and iterate on the solution characterize the behavior.
同时(在模拟中)进行这样的机动 迭代方案 让行为特征化
So we can not only solve for it, we can then build up a data set on an object.
所以我们不仅可以解决它 我们还可以在一个物体上建立一个数据集
and say what's normal and what's not normal for a guy.
并说什么是正常的 什么是不正常的
But we saw this
但是我们看到了这个
so they kind of killed their inclination even further
那么 它们差不多是进一步减少了倾角
and if you notice they started to slide ever so slightly to the west.
如果你注意到 他们开始非常轻微地向西滑行
and if you look right now.
而如果你现在看
TJS-3 AKM is right where the TJS-3 had been.
TJS-3 AKM就在TJS-3以前的位置上
So it presented a challenge to some tracking networks because...
那么这对一些追踪网络提出了挑战 因为……
Confused the observations?
这会混淆了观察结果？
You just confuse the observations.
这样只会把观察结果搞混了
We call a cross tagging.
我们称之为交叉标记
And then they killed the little westerly drift they had and they stopped.
然后它们不再向西漂移 之后停下来了
But then 48 hours later TJS-3 left.
但48小时后 TJS-3离开了
And if I drag it and they have been drifting ever since.
如果我拖动时间 从那时起 TJS-3就在漂移
They're going at about 2.5-2.6 degrees per day.
每天以2.5到2.6度的速度运动
They're going east.
TJS-3向东飞去
And they're still drifting today.
而且今天还在漂移
They're still drifting today and to..
TJS-3今天还在漂移 同时……
Their attitude is stable?
TJS-3的姿态是稳定的吗？
No this was intentional.
不 这是故意的
They did two maneuvers 12 hours apart.
间隔12小时 TJS-3做了两次机动
To go from circular here to circular here.
从这里的绕行轨道到这里的绕行轨道
One two, right. They don't want to be crossing the GEO belt.
一 二 没错 他们不想穿越GEO区域
Didn't want to be a conjunction risk.
不想成为碰撞风险
So you notice. If you imagine the GEO belt... whoops
那么你注意到了 如果你想象GEO区域
Imagine the GEO belt is at this altitude
想象一下 GEO区域在这个高度上
hmm
恩
they are below GEO altitude which is why they're going east
它们低于GEO高度 所以要往东走
with respect to the surface of the Earth's.
相对于地球表面
But they are roughly circular which is why they're not bouncing around up here.
但它们大致是圆形的轨道 这就是为什么它们没有在这里跳来跳去
But besides the fact that they're on the move the AKM stayed home.
但除了它们在移动这件事之外 AKM停下了
So a couple of things based on my ops experiences tells me
所以根据我的任务经验 会知道这么几件事
a lot of times when you launch the satellite especially the GEO
很多时候 当你发射卫星 特别是GEO的时候
you park it somewhere at like a test station
你把它停在某个地方 就像一个测试站
and you have a test program depending on the mission
而你有一个根据任务而定的测试程序
it could be a couple days a couple weeks
可能会耗时几天或几周
could be three four five months
可能是三 四 五个月
will you have a series of check out things you want to do.
你会不会有一系列你想完成的事情
You want to turn on this and turn on this and does this work
你想打开这个 打开那个 检测这个是否工作
and if I run the comm from this antenna through this amplifier to that antenna does that'll work.
如果我让通讯从这个天线通过这个放大器运行到那个天线 是否会起作用
And you do all the tests brand new satellites shake it down.
而你进行各种测试 让全新的卫星适应这种安排
That's normal and then when you're happy you then move it somewhere else.
这是正常的 然后当你满意的时候 再把它移到别的地方
Normally the test station is where your test facilities can see it.
通常测试站是在你的测试设施可以看到它的地方
It's near where you inject it into GEO.
就在你让它进入GEO的地方附近
It's where it's convenient for you.
这个地方可以方便你
And then let's say you have a global constellation.
然后假设 你有一个全球星座
you may want to move it halfway around the world for its operational mission.
你可能会想把它移到另一半的世界上 以利于它的运营任务
It depends.
这要看情况
So you do your test and then you start a drift.
那么你做你的测试 然后开始漂移
This being launched at the end of December
这是在12月底发射的
sitting here from January through mid-may
从1月到5月中旬都在那里
and then leaving has all the appearances of they've completed their on-orbit tests and check out of TJS-3.
然后离开的时候 看上去他们已经完成了TJS-3的在轨测试和检查
And it's on its way to its operational station.
它正在去往它的运营位置
Again I don't know what the mission is.
再说明一下 我不知道任务是什么
I don't know what station is.
我不知道它会移动到哪个位置上
But it sure seems like they finished the test.
但它肯定看起来像是完成了测试
They're on the way to operational station.
并正在前往运营位置的路上
Number two the AKM didn't go with it.
第二 AKM没有跟去
But based on the fact that for four months they played nice together in a very coordinated fashion.
但根据事实 四个月来 它们在一起玩得很好 非常协调
And they were launched together.
而且它们是一起发射的
It sure seems like the AKM was some sort of test object.
AKM似乎是某种测试目标
So not rendezvous in prox ops because they didn't get real close and personal and stuff.
所以不会抵近操作或交会 因为没有真正的进行近距离接触之类的东西
So it wasn't like they were trying to do a local dance around each other.
所以它们并没有试图在对方周围跳舞
Do docking.
进行对接
But there's some sort of test purpose this thing had for this guy's mission.
但AKM对TJS-3的任务具有某种测试目的
And again it appears that that purpose has been served.
而且看来这个目的已经达到了
So they left it here.
所以他们把它留在了这里
And this guy's going to his operational home.
而TJS-3要去它的运营位置了
So we'll watch where he goes.
那么我们会观察它的去向的
He's been drifting now for a little over a month.
它已经漂移了一个多月了
We'll see what happens.
我们会看到会发生了什么
Great thanks bob thanks very informative.
很好 谢谢你 Bob 你给出的信息量很大
I think you guys are gonna be keeping an eye on it
我想你们会一直关注着它
so if anything else interesting comes up we'll bring you back.
所以 如果有其他有趣的事情出现 我们会带你回来
You can tell us what's going on or an AKM itself moves or whatever.
你可以告诉我们发生了什么事 或者AKM本身运动或其他什么
Sure.
没问题
Yeah thanks again.
是的 再次感谢
All right.
好的